Ethel L. Voynich Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Ethel L. Voynich Papers 1828-1948 (bulk 1935-1948)
ML31.V75
Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960
approximately 800 items 14 containers 6.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Ethel Lillian Voynich (1864-1960) was a social activist, novelist, translator, and composer. Voynich's musical compositions, based principally on sacred or poetic texts, are represented by holograph manuscript scores, sketches, lyric sheets, printed music, and notes. The remaining materials consist of subject files on musicological topics, research materials, and a handful of programs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Chomiński, Józef M.; Gurney, Ivor, 1890-1937.; Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960--Archives.; Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960--Manuscripts.; Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960.; Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960.; Voynich, E. L. (Ethel Lillian), 1864-1960. Musical works. Selections.
Subjects
Music--Manuscripts.
Form/Genre
Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Anne M. Nill, 1961.
Custodial History
Ethel Voynich bequeathed her belongings to Anne M. Nill in 1943, seventeen years prior to her passing. Some sources suggest Anne was manager of Wilfred Voynich's bookstore in Soho Square, London, in the early 1900s. In 1914, Wilfred allegedly brought Anne, then a secretary, to New York to help with a new store that he had established. Ethel remained in England at the time, but later joined them in New York in 1920. Other sources claim that Anne, born in Buffalo, New York in 1894, was an American citizen who made her professional acquaintance with Wilfred Voynich in New York City circa 1921. Anne and Ethel developed a lasting friendship, with Anne providing editorial assistance for Ethel's later writings.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Ethel L. Voynich Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Ethel Lillian Voynich (1864-1960) was a social activist, novelist, translator, and composer. Born May 11, 1864, in County Cork, Ireland, Ethel Lilian Boole was the youngest of the five daughters of George Boole (1815-1864) and Mary Everest Boole (1832-1916). George Boole was an eminent mathematician whose theories (Boolean Logic) were instrumental to the development of modern technologies, including digital recording and the Internet. Mary Boole was an eccentric mathematician, teacher, and writer whose books on teaching mathematics to children became milestones in education. Despite their strong intellectual background, George and Mary lived in acute poverty and sent Ethel to live with her uncle, Charles Boole, in Lancashire. The years of physical abuse from Charles that followed eventually became the basis for her 1901 novel, Jack Raymond.
At the age of eighteen, Ethel traveled to Berlin and enrolled in the Hochschule der Musik in an effort to pursue her childhood love of music. Her studies of piano and composition from 1882-1885, however, were overshadowed by her newfound interest in revolutionary literature and political activism. Inspired by the plight of Russian prisoners under Tzarist rule, Ethel moved to St. Petersburg in 1887, where she made ends meet teaching English and music, dedicating any remaining time to helping suffering prisoners and peasants. After two years of committed charitable, revolutionary activity, Ethel returned to London, where she made the acquaintance of Polish patriot, antiquarian, and bibliophile Wilfred Michael Voynich, then a Russian fugitive. The two lived together and worked on various revolutionary endeavors for many years, eventually marrying in 1902.
During this period, Ethel established herself as both a writer and a translator of Russian literature into English. Her first published translation, Stories from Garshin, was released in 1893, followed by The humor of Russia (1985), and Nihilism as it is (1895). Her most famous novel, The Gadfly (1897), was later made into a film in the Soviet Union with a score by Dmitiri Shostakovich. Ethel remained musically active as well, becoming a member of the Society of Woman Musicians, an organization founded by composer Marion Scott in 1911. Through Scott, she established a close relationship with composer and war poet Ivor Gurney, an inspirational force behind her literary and musical compositions. Following her immigration to New York City around 1920, Ethel began intensive studies in composition and orchestration. These contributed to her creation of a variety of sacred vocal and instrumental works in the 1920s, including Babylon, Jerusalem, and Epitaph in Ballad Form.
In March 1930, husband Wilfred Voynich, by now an established New York bookseller, passed away from respiratory illness. Ethel moved in with his secretary and shop manager Anne M. Nill shortly thereafter, and the pair lived together for nearly thirteen years in Manhattan. Ethel continued to write, translate, and compose. Her last work, Put Off Thy Shoes, was published in 1945. The remainder of her life was spent reaping the rewards of her signature best-seller, The Gadfly, a work that had, unbeknownst to her at the time, single-handedly established Ethel's reputation as an American literary hero in the Soviet Union. Royalties from the novel and its derivative films enabled her to live a robust intellectual life until her death in 1960 at age ninety-six.
Scope and Content Note
The Ethel L. Voynich Papers span the period 1835 to 1948, with the majority of the materials dating from 1928-1948. Voynich's musical compositions, based principally on sacred or poetic texts, are represented by holograph manuscript scores, sketches, lyric sheets, and notes. Works are arranged alphabetically by title, with sources of texts identified if possible. The remaining materials consist of subject files on musicological topics and a handful of programs. Included is documentation of Voynich's studies with musicologist Josef Chominski, work done at the Pius X School of Liturgical Music in New York, research conducted at the New York Public Library, and her associations with notable Gloucester composer-poet Ivor Gurney.
Organization of the Ethel L. Voynich Papers
The Ethel L. Voynich Papers are organized in three series:
Music, 1916-1948
Subject Files, 1937-1941
Miscellany, 1835-1946
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563503
Container List
- Music, 1916-1948 (Box 1-12)
  - Babylon (voices, chorus, orchestra)
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Photocopied manuscript full score (Box 11)
    - Manuscript short score (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Sketches and notes (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Blue Bunny's book (voice, piano)
    - Manuscript piano-vocal score, Laid in: sketches and lyric sheets (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Blue Bunny's influenza blues (voice, piano)
    - Manuscript piano-vocal score (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Bunny dance (piano)
    - Sketch (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Come near (voice, piano)
    - 2 manuscript piano-vocal scores (Box-folder 1/4)
  - The crossroads (voices, band)
    - Manuscript full score, Laid in: sketches and notes (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Cubby lion's childhood (voice, piano)
    - 3 manuscript piano-vocal scores, Laid in: sketches (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Desire in Spring (voice, piano), Music: Ivor Gurney; text: Francis Ledwidge
    - Manuscript piano-vocal score in the hand of I. Gurney, Inscribed from Gurney to Voynich (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Ego sum pastor bonus (voices), By Waclaw Szamotulski
    - Photocopied copyist manuscript vocal score, Musical analysis in pencil (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Epitaph in ballad form (voices, orchestra), Text: Francois Villon
    - 3 manuscript full scores, Laid in: sketches and lyric sheets (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Photocopied manuscript full score (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Five Elizabethan songs. Sleep (voice, piano), By Ivor Gurney
    - Printed piano-vocal score, Inscribed from Gurney to Voynich (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Give ear, o ye heavens (voices, 8 parts) see also I sing of a maiden, Text: Deuteronomy 32:1,2
    - Manuscript vocal score, Laid in: sketches (Box-folder 1/10)
  - The golden net (voices) see also Who is this?, Text: William Blake
    - 4 manuscript vocal scores (Box-folder 2/1)
    - 3 photocopied manuscript vocal scores, Laid in: lyric sheets (Box-folder 2/2)
  - I sing of a maiden (women's voices, 8 parts) see also Give ear, o ye heavens, Text: traditional, 15th century
    - Manuscript vocal score, Laid in: sketches (Box-folder 8/3)
  - I sing of a maiden (women's voices, 16 parts) see also Give ear, o ye heavens, Text: traditional, 15th century
    - Manuscript vocal score, Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Jerusalem (voices, chorus, orchestra), Text: traditional hymn
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Manuscript full score, Laid in: lyric sheets and notes (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Manuscript full score, Movements I and II only (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Manuscript full score, Movement V only; On cover: Re-written 1923 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Photocopied manuscript full score, Annotations (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Photocopied manuscript full score, Annotations (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Manuscript short score (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Manuscript piano-vocal score, Miscellaneous movements (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Sketches (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Sketches (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Jerusalem (women's voices, orchestra), Text: traditional hymn
    - Manuscript short score, On title page: Piano and vocal score (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Lenten is come (women's voices, piano), Text: traditional
    - Printed piano-vocal score proof (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Little lamb (voice, piano), Music: Mary Wilkes; text: William Blake
    - Photocopied manuscript piano-vocal score, Laid in: notes (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Little suite (woodwinds, harp)
    - Manuscript score and parts, Laid in: sketches (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Manuscript score, Laid in: notes (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Man octapartite (voices, double chorus, strings), Text: Irish traditional
    - Sketches and lyric sheets (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Mass in B Minor, By J.S. Bach
    - Printed score, Annotations; Bound, personalized copy (Box-folder 4/1)
  - O mortal folk (chorus), Text: Stephen Hawkes
    - Manuscript vocal score (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Manuscript vocal score, Laid in: lyric sheets (Box-folder 4/3)
  - On Wenlock Edge (voice, strings, piano), Music: Ralph Vaughan Williams; text: Alfred Edward Houseman; Transcribed by Ivor Gurney
    - Manuscript vocal score in the hand of I. Gurney, Unfinished (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Our lady sings (double chorus), Text: Jerusalem, my happy home
    - Printed vocal score, Annotations (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Pinky's Declaration of Independence (song for the 4th of July)
    - Manuscript lead sheet (Box-folder 4/6)
  - The riders: symphonic cantata in 4 movements
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Parts (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Saltaire tunes
    - Manuscript lead sheets, Laid in: postcard and crayon drawing from 1937 September 4-8 visit to Saltaire, NY (Box-folder 5/3)
  - So shuts the marigold (voices), Text: William Browne of Tavistock
    - 3 manuscript vocal scores (Box-folder 5/4)
  - The submerged city: cantata for solo baritone, mixed choir, and orchestra, Text: Aleksey Stepanovich Khomyakov
    - Manuscript full score, Laid in: sketches and lyric sheet (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Manuscript full score (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Manuscript full score, Incomplete (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Manuscript short score, On cover: Piano score (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Tollite portas (Lift up your heads) (voices), Text: William Byrd
    - Manuscript vocal score (English) (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Manuscript vocal score (French) (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Unwelcome (voice, piano), Text: Mary Coleridge
    - 2 manuscript piano-vocal scores (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Victimae paschali laudes (voices, organ)
    - Manuscript score for voice and organ (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Wilfred's birthday song
    - Manuscript lead sheet (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Who is this? see also The golden net
    - Manuscript vocal score, Laid in: lyric sheet (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Unidentified
    - Sketches (Box-folder 5/10)
- Subject Files, 1937-1941 (Box 6, 13-14)
  - Chominski, Josef Michal, 1937-1941, E.L. Voynich's notes from studies with Chominski (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Folk songs: Czeck (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Folk songs: Polish (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Folk songs: Russian (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Folk songs: Ukranian (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Folk songs: other than Slavonic (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Military music (Box-folder 13/6)
  - Musical diagrams: relationships to intervals (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Pius X School of Liturgical Music (Box-folder 14/1-2)
  - Polyphony: evolution of (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Polyphony: France, Netherlands, Germany, Spain (Box-folder 14/4)
  - Primitive, exotic, ancient music (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Theoretical studies, nature, primitive (Box-folder 14/5)
- Miscellany, 1835-1946 (Box 6, 14)
  - Gurney, Ivor, Clippings (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Programs
    - Miscellaneous programs, 1932-1946 (Box-folder 14/7)
    - Theatre Royal, Covent Garden, 1835 July 3, Performers include Maria Taglioni, Guilietta Grisi, and others (Box-folder 6/4)